Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection 1923-2015
AFC 2008/005
Ritchie, Jean, 1922-2015
Pickow, George, 1922-2010
78,521 items
119 containers
108 linear feet
manuscripts: 41,650 sheets
7 wire sound reels: analog
approximately 642 sound tape reels; various sizes
1 sound only videocassette (VHS)
approximately 766 film elements: analog, black and white, color; various sizes
approximately 255 videocassettes; various sizes
approximately 35,000 photographs, various formats: black and white, color; various sizes
1 award
approximately 100 lanyards
approximately 100 buttons
1 Appalachian dulcimer; length 808 mm
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Multiformat materials that document the careers of folksinger and folklorist Jean Ritchie, and her husband, photographer and filmmaker George Pickow, from the 1940s to 2000.
Acquisition
Jean Ritchie and George Pickow, 2008-2011; Pickow Family Trust, 2013; Peter Pickow, 2015.
Accruals
Accruals were received from 2011-2015.
Related Material
Jean Ritchie Folk Music of Ireland and Scotland Recordings (BCA 0145 SAA 145), Berea College Special Collections & Archives, Berea, KY. https://bereaarchives.libraryhost.com/repositories/2/resources/503
Jean Ritchie papers, Port Washington Public Library Local History Center, Port Washington, New York. https://localhistory.pwpl.org/wp-content/uploads/Ritchie_Jean.pdf
Jean Ritchie and George Pickow Collection, ca. 1940-2010 (SC23220), New York State Library, Manuscripts and Special Collections, Albany, New York. https://nyst.sirsi.net/uhtbin/cgisirsi/x/0/0/5?searchdata1=ocn969909498
Ritchie-Pickow collection, Photographs and music relating to the visit of Jean Ritchie and George Pickow to Ireland, 1952-1953, University of Galway Library Archives. https://archivesearch.library.universityofgalway.ie/nuig/calmview/Record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&id=P1
Access and Restrictions
The Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Jean Ritchie
Jean Ritchie was born on December 8, 1922 in Viper, Kentucky, the youngest of 14 in a family of singers and musicians. She attended Cumberland Junior College and later the University of Kentucky; at the latter she graduated Phi Beta Kappa in 1946, with a B.A. in social work. She taught children music at Henry Street Settlement in New York City, and it was there that she met Alan Lomax, who recorded her for the Archive of American Folk Song in 1951. Jean Ritchie was involved in the folk music scene, performing with numerous others including Woody Guthrie and Oscar Brand. She married George Pickow in 1950, and together they built her career. They traveled together during Jean's Fulbright award year abroad in 1952-1953, as she recorded folk singers in Great Britain and Ireland, such as Seamus Ennis; and documented folk customs such as the May Day hobby horse (Obby Oss) in Padstow, Cornwall. Jean was a published author (among her best known works is her memoir and songbook Singing Family of the Cumberlands ), about her own family and their musical legacy. She recorded over thirty albums, performed with countless individuals and groups over the span of a 50-plus year career, popularized the dulcimer (she and George had a dulcimer-manufacturing business), served on the board for the Newport Folk Festival (circa 1963), and received a National Endowment for the Arts National Heritage Fellowship (2002). She earned high regard and praise both in the U.S. and abroad as an authentic representative of Appalachian music traditions. She died June 1, 2015 in Berea, Kentucky.
George Pickow
George Pickow, born in Los Angeles, California, in 1922 and raised in Brooklyn, New York, began his career in photography in the 1940s, after studying painting at Cooper Union, in New York. He built his career working for the Three Lions photo agency, publishing stock photos for magazines as varied as Look, National Geographic, The Rotarian, Today's Health, and various "true stories"-styled detective magazines. He worked as a documentary filmmaker in various roles (both in front of the camera and behind it, as a director), most notably for Festival (1967) and documentaries on the British May Day and Padstow Obby Oss traditions. In the 1950s he worked with Paddy Clancy and Lou Gordon as presenters of Swapping Song Fair, which began as rent-raising midnight shows at Cherry Lane Theatre. With Jean he ran the dulcimer-making business (his uncle made the dulcimers) and the recording label Greenhays. He photographed Jean as well as many of her contemporaries (Woody Guthrie, Doc Watson, and Mary Travers, among others), and his photos also illustrated many of Jean's books. He photographed dozens of album covers for the popular stereophonic albums of the 1950s, as well as for Jean's albums. He died in 2010.
Scope and Content
Papers, sound recordings, film, video, and photographs created by and documenting the careers of folksinger and folklorist, Jean Ritchie and her husband, photographer and filmmaker, George Pickow from the 1940s to 2000. Includes sound and video recordings of folk music, folk songs, folk tales, beliefs, conversations, and family stories of Jean Ritchie, her siblings, and extended family from Viper, Kentucky; Appalachian storytelling by Richard Chase, Cratis Williams and others; documentation of church services, sermons, and hymns in Kentucky. Includes documentation of Jean Ritchie's recording career at lectures, folklore seminars, festivals, concerts, and on radio broadcasts; Ritchie and Pickow's field recordings made in England, Scotland, Northern Ireland, and Ireland of performers including Jeannie Robertson, Hamish Henderson, Seamus Ennis, Francis McPeake, Michael Cronin, Isla Cameron, A. L. Lloyd, Ewan MacColl, Sarah Makem, and others. Includes photographs and film taken at various locations in the United States by George Pickow and recordings of many American performers including Dave Sear, Sam Eskin, Oscar Brand, Bessie Jones, and many others. One of Jean Ritchie's dulcimers and materials from her memorial service, June 14, 2015, were donated by her son Peter Pickow in 2015. This dulcimer was made by J. Edward Thomas of Bath, Knott County, Kentucky, 1923 November 16; it is described in L. Allen Smith, A Catalogue of Pre-Revival Appalachian Dulcimers (Columbia and London: University of Missouri Press, 1983), no. E8, p. 85.
Arrangement
Organized by format. Most of the headings on folders were transcribed as received from the donors. Correspondence is arranged chronologically and appears in other locations besides Subseries 1.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Pickow, George; Pickow, George--Ethnomusicological collections.; Ritchie, Jean; Ritchie, Jean--Ethnomusicological collections.
Subjects
Appalachian dulcimer music.; Appalachian dulcimer--Kentucky--Knott County.; Field recordings--Great Britain.; Field recordings--United States.; Folk festivals.; Folk music--England.; Folk music--Ireland.; Folk music--Kentucky.; Folk music--Northern Ireland.; Folk music--Scotland.; Folk music--United States.; Folk singers--Kentucky.; Folk songs, English--Kentucky.; Folk songs, Irish--Northern Ireland.; Folk songs, Scottish Gaelic--Scotland.; Folklore--England.; Folklore--Kentucky.; Folklorists--Great Britain.; Folklorists--United States.; Hymns, English--Kentucky.; Storytelling--Appalachian Region.
Places
Appalachian Region--Social life and customs.; Kentucky--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Film.; Manuscripts.; Musical instruments.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence
    Includes handwritten and typed correspondence on various types of paper, including a repurposed dust jacket for the book And to Think I Saw It on Mulberry Street. Only two items are photocopies; all others are original. Due to the organizational nature of the collection, correspondence is also elsewhere in the collection, outside the designated subseries.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Ritchie family
      Correspondence received for years as indicated.
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1913, 1916 (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1917 (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1918 (Box-folder 1/3)
        The photo from this folder has been relocated to Series 3.
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1919, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1923-1928 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1931-1939, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1940 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1941 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1942 (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1943 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1944 (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1945 (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1946 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1947 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1948 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1949 (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1949 (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, circa 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1950 (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1950 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1951 (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1951 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1952 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1952 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1953 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1953 (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1954 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1954 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/3), 1955 (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/3), 1955 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (3/3), 1955 (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/3), 1956 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/3), 1956 (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (3/3), 1956 (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1957 (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1957 (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1958 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1958 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/3), 1959 (Box-folder 4/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/3), 1959 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (3/3), 1959 (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, circa 1950-1959 (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1960 (Box-folder 4/11)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1960 (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1961 (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1961 (Box-folder 5/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1962 (Box-folder 5/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1962 (Box-folder 5/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1963 (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1964 (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1965 (Box-folder 5/8)
        Also includes Mallie Ritchie's 1965 engagement calendar, with notes about family activities and events.
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1966 (Box-folder 5/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/2), 1967 (Box-folder 5/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/2), 1967 (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1968 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1969 (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, circa 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1970 (Box-folder 6/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1971 (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1972 (Box-folder 6/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1973 (Box-folder 6/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1974 (Box-folder 6/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1975 (Box-folder 6/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1976 (Box-folder 6/11)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1977 (Box-folder 7/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1978 (Box-folder 7/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1979 (Box-folder 7/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, circa 1970-1979 (Box-folder 7/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1980 (Box-folder 7/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 7/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1986 (Box-folder 7/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 7/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1989 (Box-folder 7/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 7/10)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 7/11)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1995 (Box-folder 7/12)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1996 (Box-folder 7/13)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 7/14)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family, 2001-2006 (Box-folder 7/15)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (1/10), undated (Box-folder 8/1)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (2/10), undated (Box-folder 8/2)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (3/10), undated (Box-folder 8/3)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (4/10), undated (Box-folder 8/4)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (5/10), undated (Box-folder 8/5)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (6/10), undated (Box-folder 8/6)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (7/10), undated (Box-folder 8/7)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (8/10), undated (Box-folder 8/8)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (9/10), undated (Box-folder 8/9)
      - Correspondence: Ritchie family (10/10), undated (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Business and Personal
      Letters, postcards, email printouts, event announcements, and ephemera. Files that were organized into specific groups follow the general correspondence in this subseries.
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1918, 1926, circa 1936 (Box-folder 9/1)
        Also includes a blank postcard (circa 1936).
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1942 (Box-folder 9/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1943 (Box-folder 9/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1943 (Box-folder 9/4)
        Also includes a photo (a photocopy here, and the original moved to Series 3).
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1944 (Box-folder 9/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1945 (Box-folder 9/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1946 (Box-folder 9/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1946 (Box-folder 9/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1947 (Box-folder 10/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1947 (Box-folder 10/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 10/3)
        Includes a one-page handwritten letter from Woody Guthrie to Alan Lomax.
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 10/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 10/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1951 (Box-folder 10/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1952 (Box-folder 10/7)
        Also includes a letter on American Folklore Society letterhead from MacEdward Leach.
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1953 (Box-folder 10/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1954 (Box-folder 10/9)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1955 (Box-folder 11/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1955 (Box-folder 11/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1956 (Box-folder 11/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1957 (Box-folder 11/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1958 (Box-folder 11/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1959 (Box-folder 11/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 11/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1960 (Box-folder 12/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1961 (Box-folder 12/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/3), 1962 (Box-folder 12/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/3), 1962 (Box-folder 12/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (3/3), 1962 (Box-folder 12/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1963 (Box-folder 12/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1963 (Box-folder 13/1)
        Also includes a signed contract for the Newport Folk Festival, plus a ticket and a child's ID/pass for Jonathan Pickow.
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1964 (Box-folder 13/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1964 (Box-folder 13/3)
        Also includes photos from the John R. Wisdom family; photocopies are in this folder, and the originals are in Series 3.
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1965 (Box-folder 13/4)
        Also includes a family tree from Mrs. Joseph L. Barnes (a relative of Jean).
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1966 (Box-folder 13/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1967 (Box-folder 13/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1968 (Box-folder 13/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1969 (Box-folder 14/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 14/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1970 (Box-folder 14/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1971 (Box-folder 14/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1972 (Box-folder 14/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1972 (Box-folder 14/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1973 (Box-folder 14/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1973 (Box-folder 15/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1974 (Box-folder 15/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/2), 1975 (Box-folder 15/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/2), 1975 (Box-folder 15/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/3), 1976 (Box-folder 15/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/3), 1976 (Box-folder 15/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (3/3), 1976 (Box-folder 15/7)
        Also includes photos (photocopies here, and the originals moved to Series 3).
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1977 (Box-folder 16/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1978 (Box-folder 16/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1979 (Box-folder 16/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 16/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1980 (Box-folder 16/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1980 (Box-folder 16/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1981 (Box-folder 16/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1982 (Box-folder 16/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1983 (Box-folder 16/9)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1984 (Box-folder 16/10)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1985 (Box-folder 17/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1986 (Box-folder 17/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1987 (Box-folder 17/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1988 (Box-folder 17/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1989 (Box-folder 17/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 17/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1990 (Box-folder 17/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1991 (Box-folder 17/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1992 (Box-folder 17/9)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1993 (Box-folder 17/10)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1994 (Box-folder 17/11)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1995 (Box-folder 18/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1996 (Box-folder 18/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1997 (Box-folder 18/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1998 (Box-folder 18/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1999 (Box-folder 18/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 1990-1999 (Box-folder 18/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2000 (Box-folder 18/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2001 (Box-folder 18/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2002 (Box-folder 18/9)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2003 (Box-folder 18/10)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2004 (Box-folder 19/1)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2005 (Box-folder 19/2)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2006 (Box-folder 19/3)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2007 (Box-folder 19/4)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2008 (Box-folder 19/5)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2009 (Box-folder 19/6)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2010 (Box-folder 19/7)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2011 (Box-folder 19/8)
      - Correspondence: business and personal, 2000-2011 (Box-folder 19/9)
      - Shelby House reunion, 1963, 1988, 1996 (Box-folder 19/10)
        Correspondence and related updates regarding a college reunion.
      - Correspondence: business and personal (1/3), undated (Box-folder 19/11)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (2/3), undated (Box-folder 19/12)
      - Correspondence: business and personal (3/3), undated (Box-folder 20/1)
      - Early New York period (1/2), 1942-1950 (Box-folder 20/2)
      - Early New York period (2/2), 1942-1950 (Box-folder 20/3)
      - Letters and happenings, circa 1947-1962, undated (Box-folder 20/4)
      - Jean's old letters (1/2), 1943-2010 (Box-folder 20/5)
        Correspondence in these two folders was received thus from the donor. The original heading was "Jean's old letters (and some of Edna's)." The bulk of the correspondence dates from the 1940s.
      - Jean's old letters (2/2), 1943-2010 (Box-folder 20/6)
        See the description for box-folder 20/5.
      - Correspondence: Germany, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 20/7)
        Letters regarding concerts and a dulcimer workshop Jean would give in Germany.
      - Eleanor Greenlief, 1981-2009 (Box-folder 20/8)
        The original folder header was "Eleanor's letters."
      - George Pickow: letters sent and received, 1953, 1987, undated (Box-folder 21/1)
        The contents of this folder, originally titled "Letters - Pickow," are as received from the donor. Only one item is from 1987.
      - Oss 'Oss Wee 'Oss (The Padstow Hobby Horse): correspondence and related materials, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 21/2)
        Also includes letters, receipts, etc.
      - George's and Jean's letters to each other, and correspondence from others (1/7), 1934, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 21/3)